{"tossups": [{"question": "Sybil Ludington is nicknamed the \u201cfemale\u201d counterpart of this figure. William Dawes and this man were given similar tasks by Joseph Warren. This man\u2019s most famous act occurred on \u201cthe eighteenth of April, in Seventy-Five\u201d and is the subject of a Henry Wadsworth Longfellow poem that states \"one if by land, and two if by sea.\" For ten points, name this silversmith who warned of approaching British troops during a \u201cmidnight ride.\u201d", "answer": "Paul <b><u>Revere</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these structures built by the Axumite Kingdom was taken to Rome but returned to Ethiopia after Italy signed a UN agreement. The earliest known type of this object was comprised of 120 metric tons of red granite, and was meant to commemorate Senusret I in Heliopolis. These structures were said to symbolize the sun god Ra and are topped with a pyramid-shaped capstone. For ten points, name this type of tall, four-sided, monument from Ancient Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Obelisk</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this nation, Paul Sch\u00e4fer [[SHAY-fer]] led an agrarian community known as Dignity Colony that doubled as a post-war refuge for Nazis. The economic policy of a regime in this nation was influenced by the <em>El Ladrillo</em> [[lah-DREE-yoh]] study, first published by the \"Chicago Boys.\" A left-wing leader likely killed himself while defending this nation's Moneda [[moh-NEH-dah]] Palace. Augusto Pinochet [[pee-noh-SHEH]] took power in a 1973 coup in, for ten points, what South American nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Chile</u></b> (accept Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Chile</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A painting of this ruler in his study shows a clock in the background at 4:13 a.m and a law code on a table. Paul Delaroche [[deh-lah-ROHSH]] painted a more realistic version of a painting where the names of Charlemagne and Hannibal can be seen on rocks below this leader. That painting by Jacques-Louis David [JAHK LOO-wee DAH-veed]] shows this ruler crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French Emperor depicted at battles like Austerlitz and Waterloo.", "answer": "<b><u>Napoleon</u></b> Bonaparte (or <b><u>Napoleon</u></b> I of France)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In this ecosystem, deaths attributed to the mountain pine beetle created ladder fuels that resulted in a 1988 wildfire. Drawings and paintings from the Hayden Expedition and the photographs of William Henry Jackson helped make the case for this place's status. The 4900 bison which live here comprise a namesake herd that is the largest in the United States. In March 1872, the first national park status was granted to, for ten points, what Wyoming-centered home of Old Faithful?", "answer": "<b><u>Yellowstone</u></b> National Park", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "An ancient Indo-European example of these systems from the Vu\u010dedol [[VOO-cheh-dol]] culture in Croatia was based on Orion. According to a popular myth, the institution of one of these systems by Chesterfield's Act in 1750 resulted in riots around London. Examples of these systems in Europe are named for Julius Caesar and Pope Gregory XIII [[the thirteenth]]. For ten points, name these systems used to organize time into lunar months.", "answer": "<b><u>Calendar</u></b> (accept Vu\u010dedol <b><u>calendar</u></b>; accept Julian <b><u>calendar</u></b>; accept Gregorian <b><u>calendar</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man's manager, \"Colonel\" Tom Parker, stopped him from playing Tony in the 1961 film adaptation of <em>West Side Story</em>. Ed Sullivan initially declared this man's performances \"unfit for family viewing\" after witnessing his \"gyrations\" during a performance on the <em>Milton Berle Show</em>. In 2019, the city of Memphis funded an expansion of this man's estate, Graceland. The \"King of Rock n' Roll\" was, for ten points, what Tennessee singer of Hound Dog\" and \"Heartbreak Hotel\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Elvis</u><u>Presley</u></b> (or <b><u>Elvis</u></b> Aaron <b><u>Presley</u></b>; accept either underline portion)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man used the proceeds from his Lancaster Caramel Company to start his most famous business. This man built a namesake \"Industrial\" boarding school in a company town he established in Pennsylvania in 1903. During World War Two, this man\u2019s factories produced \"Ration D Bars,\" a special type of confectionary designed to resist melting. For ten points, name this American founder of a chocolate bar and confectionary company.", "answer": "Milton Snavely <b><u>Hershey</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The only known recording of this man is him repeating the first line of \"La Marseillaise\" in mocking French. The Ems Dispatch was purposefully released to the press by this man to discredit the government of Napoleon III. This minister annexed the province of Alsace-Lorraine following the Franco-Prussian War. The rise of Wilhelm II led to the deposition of, for ten points, which \"Iron Chancellor\" who masterminded the unification of Germany?", "answer": "Otto von <b><u>Bismarck</u></b> (accept Junker Otto Eduard Leopold von <b><u>Bismarck</u></b>; accept Otto, Prince of <b><u>Bismarck</u></b>, Count of Bismarck-Sch\u00f6nhausen, Duke of Lauenburg; or Otto F\u00fcrst von <b><u>Bismarck</u></b>, Graf von Bismarck-Sch\u00f6nhausen, Herzog zu Lauenburg)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was able to flee Nazi Germany after his consultation and analysis of the royal Princess Marie Bonaparte led to a lifelong friendship between the two. The heiress to Tiffany & Co., Dorothy Burlingham, was in a relationship with this man's daughter and fellow psychoanalyst, Anna. This man developed the idea of the id, ego, and superego, which were founding ideas of psychoanalysis. For ten points, name this Austrian psychologist who wrote <em>The Interpretation of Dreams</em>.", "answer": "Sigmund <b><u>Freud</u></b> (or Sigismund Schlomo <b><u>Freud</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "One of this man's speeches included what is now known as the \"Economic Bill of Rights.\" This man served as assistant secretary of the Navy during the Wilson administration. This president attempted to curb the \"Four Horsemen\" by packing the Supreme Court. The Tennessee Valley Authority and Social Security Administration were part of this president's main domestic program. For ten points, name this four-term president who promoted the New Deal.", "answer": "<b><u>F</u></b>ranklin D(elano) <b><u>Roosevelt</u></b> (accept <b><u>FDR</u></b>; prompt on 'Roosevelt')", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This geographic point was supposedly first explored by the Greek Eudoxus [[yoo-DOX-us]] around 130 BC. This geographic point was believed to be home to the <em>Flying</em> <em>Dutchman</em>, a pirate ship that haunted sailors, and is located in present-day Table Mountain National Park. The man who named this entity gives his name to a beach located on it. For ten points, name this cape in South Africa discovered by Bartolomeu Dias that was considered a safe haven for early sailors.", "answer": "Cape of <b><u>Good Hope</u></b> (or Kaap die <b><u>Goeie Hoop</u></b>; or Kaap de <b><u>Goede Hoop</u></b>; or Cabo da <b><u>Boa Esperan\u00e7a</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man, who spent five years in exile in the Netherlands, argued that \"the end of law is...to preserve and enlarge freedom.\" While serving as a secretary, this man authored the Fundamental Constitutions of Carolina. Thomas Jefferson included many of this man's ideas in the Declaration of Independence, although he edited \"property\" to \"the pursuit of happiness.\" For ten points, name this British \"Father of Liberalism\" who wrote two Treatises on Government.", "answer": "John <b><u>Locke</u> </b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This river contains Margaret Island, formerly a base for the Knights of Saint John. The mouth of this river, which was known as Okeanos Potamos in antiquity, contains Apollo's sacred island of Alba. This river's basin was the site of the Vin\u010da [[VEEN-tsuh]] culture, and was crossed by Darius the Great in order to invade the Scythian [[SKIHTH-yen]] realm. The Dacians were separated from the Roman Empire by, for ten points, what river that now runs through European capitals like Budapest and Vienna?", "answer": "<b><u>Danube</u></b> River (or <b><u>Donau</u></b>; accept <b><u>Donaj</u></b>; accept <b><u>Duna</u></b>; accept <b><u>Istros</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "To advertise this city at the 1904 World's Fair, Giuseppe Moretti created the tallest cast-iron statue in the world depicting Vulcan wielding a hammer. This city's mining significance gave the local KKK chapter easy access to dynamite, allowing them to terrorize Black citizens in the 16th Street Baptist Church bombing. In a call for direct action against segregation, Martin Luther King, Jr. wrote the treatise \"Letters from [this city's] Jail.\" For ten points, name this industrial Alabama city.", "answer": "<b><u>Birmingham</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An emperor of this dynasty established the Four Commanderies in Korea, the only successful Chinese occupation of the peninsula. This dynasty's dominance of Vietnam was temporarily undermined by the Trung Sisters' rebellion. This dynasty was briefly interrupted by the Xin [[SHIN]] Dynasty of Wang Mang. This dynasty's collapse led to the Three Kingdoms period. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese dynasty that shares its name with the country's majority ethnic group.", "answer": "<b><u>Han</u></b> Dynasty (or <b><u>H\u00e0n</u></b>ch\u00e1o)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A statue of this man was commissioned in the United States for the thousandth anniversary of the Althing. The tale of the lost merchant Bjarni Herj\u00f3lfsson [[BYAR-nee hare-YOHLF-son]] inspired this man to travel west. This explorer encountered the <em>Skraelings</em> [[SKRAY-lings]], who killed his brother Thorvald in a skirmish outside of L'Anse aux Meadows [[LAHN see MEH-doh]]. The region of Vinland was discovered by, for ten points, which Norse explorer and son of Erik the Red?", "answer": "<b><u>Leif</u></b> Erikson (accept <b><u>Leif</u></b> the Lucky; or <b><u>Leif</u></b>r hinn Heppni; prompt on \"Erikson\")  Leif Erikson's father, Erik the Red, is credited with founding the first European settlement on this large semi-arctic island, which in 2009 became autonomous from Denmark.  ANSWER: <b><u>Greenland</u></b> (accept <b><u>Kalaallit Nunaat</u></b>; or <b><u>Gr\u00f8nland</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A governor of this state, who ran in the 2016 presidential primaries using the slogan \"Our American Revival,\" lost a reelection bid to Democratic educator Tony Evers. The protests following the murder of Jacob Blake led to unrest in this state's city of Kenosha, which was followed by the Kyle Rittenhouse incident. Scott Walker once governed, for ten points, what northern state that saw protests in the cities of Madison and Milwaukee?", "answer": "<b><u>Wisconsin</u> </b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This U.S. Constitutional amendment was ratified following a vote in Nebraska.</u></b> <b><u>Congress passed the Volstead [[VOHL-sted]] Act to (+)</u> enforce this amendment\u2019s provisions. This amendment resulted from decades of activism by groups like the Anti-Saloon League and Woman's Christian Temperance (*) </b>Union, though in 1933 it became the only amendment in U.S. history to be repealed. For ten points, name this constitutional amendment that began Prohibition and banned alcohol in the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Eighteen</u></b>th Amendment (or Amendment <b><u>XVIII</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Langobards, who once dominated Italy, claimed this deity saw them first</u></b> <b><u>thing on the morning of a battle, granting them victory over the Vandals. Roman</u></b> <b><u>interaction with the Suebians [[SWEH-byens]] led (+)</u> to their conflating this god with Mercury. This deity was often associated with hanged men due to having hanged himself from Yggdrasil [[EEG-druh-sil]] to gain knowledge. The word Wednesday (*) </b>derives from, for ten points, what chief Nordic deity?", "answer": "<b><u>Odin</u></b> (accept <b><u>Woden</u></b>; or <b><u>Wutan</u></b>; or <b><u>Wotan</u></b>; or <b><u>Wodan</u></b>az)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>Leather examples of these object are used in a form of theatre performed by</u></b> <b><u>the Kannada people to retell stories like the</u> </b><em><b><u>Ramayana</u></b></em><b><u>.</u> </b><em><b><u>Taiko</u></b></em><b><u> [[tah-EE-koh]]</u></b> <b><u>drummers and</u> </b><em><b><u>tay\u016b</u></b></em><b><u> chanters are used in a form of theater using these objects named</u></b> <b><u>(*)</u> </b><em><b>bunraku</b></em><b> [[boon-RAH-koo]] native to Japan. A form of art using these figures grew in popularity in the U.S. in the vaudeville circuits of the 1800s. (*) </b>Ventriloquism is an art form using, for ten points, what objects that usually represent people and are manipulated for theatre.", "answer": "<b><u>Puppet</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Puppet</u></b> Theatre or <b><u>Puppet</u></b>try; accept <b><u>Doll</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Bunraku</u></b> or <b><u>marionette</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>After the Pledge of the Tree, this diplomat guaranteed the procession of the</u></b> <b><u>first</u> </b><em><b><u>Umrah</u></b></em><b><u> pilgrimage by negotiating the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah [[hoo-day-BEE-</u><u>yah]]. A Pagan-Jewish confederation besieged this man's capital during the Battle of</u></b> <b><u>the (+)</u> Trench, some time after this man began a war with the Quraysh [[KOO-raysh]] tribe following the Battle of Badr. The capture of (*) </b>Mecca was accomplished by, for ten points, which general and Prophet of the Islamic faith?", "answer": "<b><u>Muhammad</u></b> ibn Abdullah (accept <b><u>Mohammed</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In</u> </b><em><b><u>Map of True Places</u></b></em><b><u>, Zee Finch returns to this city to check in on her ailing</u></b> <b><u>father. In a novel set in this city, Matthew Maule lays a curse on the entire (*)</u></b> <b>Pyncheon family as well as their residence, </b><em><b>The House of the Seven Gables</b></em><b>. This city's Pickering Wharf appears in the beginning of Nathaniel Hawthorne's </b><em><b>Scarlet Letter</b></em><b>. Giles Corey is executed in an Arthur Miller (*) </b>play in, for ten points, what Massachusetts city in which a series of 1692 Witch Trials took place?", "answer": "<b><u>Salem</u></b>, Massachusetts (accept <b><u>Salem</u></b> Witch Trials)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b><u>This U.S. state's largest city was the site of Fort Christina, the capital of New</u></b> <b><u>Sweden, which occupied the lower reaches of its namesake river. This state's only</u></b> <b><u>serious engagement during the American Revolution was the Battle of Cooch's Bridge.</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> This state's \"Blue Hen's Chicks\" regiment fought at the Battle of Brandywine in a namesake county in (*) </b>Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this state which saw a British occupation of its largest city, Wilmington.", "answer": "<b><u>Delaware</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Among this document\u2019s new protections was that \u201cno freeman is to be taken or</u></b> <b><u>imprisoned\u2026 save by lawful judgment of his peers or by the law of the land.\u201d This</u></b> <b><u>document was signed on neutral territory between the royal fortress at Windsor</u></b> <b><u>Castle (+)</u> and the headquarters of a group of rebellious barons in a water-meadow alongside the River Thames [[TEMS]] called Runnymede. (*) </b>For ten points, name this document that King John signed in 1215, placing limits on royal power.", "answer": "<b><u>Magna Carta</u></b> Libertatum (accept <b><u>Great Charter</u></b> of Freedoms)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Kingdom of Kapisa [[kah-PEE-sah]] once ruled this country, which hosts</u></b> <b><u>the now-ruined Greek-inspired Buddhas of Bamiyan [[BAH-mee-yahn]]. Those</u></b> <b><u>statues were demolished in this country by a (+)</u> Deobandi [[deh-oh-BAHN-dee]] fundamentalist regime, which took power following a Soviet withdrawal. Once led by Hamid Karzai [[hah-MEED KAR-zye]], this country is often referred to as the (*) </b>\"graveyard of empires.\" In 2021, the U.S. pulled its military out of, for ten points, what Pashtun-majority Middle Eastern country controlled by the Taliban?", "answer": "Islamic Emirate of <b><u>Afghanistan</u></b> (accept Republic of <b><u>Afghanistan</u></b>; accept Da <b><u>Af\u0121\u0101nist\u0101n</u></b> Isl\u0101m\u012b Im\u0101rat; or Em\u0101rat-e Isl\u0101m\u012b-yi <b><u>Af\u0121\u0101nist\u0101n</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This woman used a papal dispensation supposedly signed by Pius II for her</u></b> <b><u>wedding in 1469 because her betrothed was her second cousin. This royal (+)</u></b> <b>woman\u2019s older half-brother, Henry IV of Castile, attempted to arrange her marriage on several occasions, but she negotiated her own marriage contract with John II (*) </b>of Navarre. For ten points, name this Catholic queen whose marriage to Ferdinand II of Aragon effectively unified Spain.", "answer": "<b><u>Isabella</u></b> I of Castile (accept Ferdinand and <b><u>Isabella</u></b>; accept <b><u>Isabella</u></b> the Catholic)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}